Finding Aid for John Butlin Martin papers, 1948-1965
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John Butlin Martin papers 1948-1965
Martin, John Butlin, 1909-
851843 Aa 2
Republican state senator, 1948-1950, from Kent County, Michigan, state auditor general, 1950-1954, unsuccessful candidate for the U.S. Senate nomination in 1952, and member of the Republican National Committee. Correspondence, newspaper clippings, speeches and printed material relating to his political career, particularly his activities on the Michigan Commission on Aging, the Michigan Constitutional Convention of 1961-1962, and the Michigan Senate campaign of 1952.
6 linear feet
1.38 GB
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of John B. Martin (donor 4739 ). Additional materials were received in 2009.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
John B. Martin was born in Grand Rapids, Michigan on October 3, 1909. He was educated at Dartmouth (A.B., 1931), Oxford (Litt. B., 1933), and the University of Michigan (J.D., 1936). After being admitted to the District of Columbia bar in 1936, Martin became legal secretary to the chairman of the Securities and Exchange Commission. From 1938 to 1941, he practiced law in Cleveland, Ohio and served as chief of the Ohio Division of Securities. During World War II, he helped to organize and later served as head of the National Office of Civilian Defense. He subsequently was commissioned in the United States Naval Reserve, serving from 1944 to 1946. Upon his discharge, he began to practice law in Grand Rapids.
Martin soon became active in Republican politics and public policy organizations. He served as state senator 1948-1950, then was elected state auditor general, serving two terms, 1950-1954. Also active in national party politics, Martin served several terms as Michigan committeeman on the Republican National Committee in the late 1950s and early 1960s
From 1957 to 1960, Martin chaired the Michigan Legislative Advisory Council on Problems of Aging. This organization later became the Michigan Commission on Aging with Martin serving first as vice-chair, then chair. Martin was also chairman of the Michigan Crime and Delinquency Council, 1960-1965, and was a delegate to Michigan's Constitutional Convention, 1961-1962, where he chaired the Committee on the Executive Branch. A life-long Republican, Martin served several terms.
The John B. Martin papers consists of correspondence, memoranda, clippings, and subject files relating to his political and organizational activities. The series in the collection are: Correspondence; Newspaper clippings; Political and Campaign Materials; Auditor General, 1950-1954; Aging organizations; Michigan Constitutional Convention, 1961-1962; Michigan Crime and Delinquency Council; Scrapbooks; Sound Recordings; Visual Materials; and Miscellaneous.
Subjects:
Aging.; Elections--Michigan--1948.; Elections--Michigan--1950.; Elections--Michigan--1956.; Kent County (Mich.); Martin, John Butlin, 1909-; Michigan. Commission on Aging.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Michigan. Insurance Bureau.; Michigan. Legislature.; Michigan. Office of the Auditor General.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Politicians--Michigan.; Republican National Convention (27th: 1960: Chicago, Ill.); Republican Party (Mich.); United States. Congress--Elections, 1952.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Political elections.; Republican Party (Mich.); Waterloo Recreation Area (Mich.)
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Martin, John Butlin, 1909-; Elections--Michigan--1952.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Republican Party (Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Contributors:
Alger, Frederick Moulton, 1907-1967.; Bartlett, Lynn M. (Lynn Mahlon), 1904-1970.; Brake, D. Hale, 1891-1979; Brown, Sanford Abbott, 1909-; Cohen, Wilbur J. (Wilbur Joseph), 1913-1987.; Dirksen, Everett McKinley.; Eldersveld, Samuel James.; Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Miller, William E. (William Edward), 1914-1983; Moody, Blair, 1902-1954.; Pollock, James K. (James Kerr), 1898-1968; Romney, George W., 1907-1995.; Sagendorph, Kent, 1902-1958; Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-1972.; Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Correspondence
  - 1950-1965, 15 folders (Box 1)
- Newspapers clippings
  - General 1950, 1952-1953, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - General 1954, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Concerning investigation of highway department land purchases and insurance audit 1954 (Box 2)
  - General 1962 (Box 2)
- Political and Campaign Materials
  - 1948 (Box 2)
  - 1950 (Box 2)
  - 1951-1952, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 1954 (Box 2)
  - 1956 1958 (Box 2)
  - 1960 (Republican National Convention, Chicago) (Box 2)
  - Speeches and press releases
    - Various campaigns 1947-1950 (Box 2)
    - 1951, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1952 (Box 2)
    - 1953 (Box 2)
    - 1954 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (largely notes for speeches), 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Complaint made by Eugene Black to the Grievance Committee of the State Bar of Michigan regarding comments about Black made by JBM as Republican campaign chairman in the Spring election of 1955 (Box 2)
- Auditor General 1950-1954
  - Financial reports of the State of Michigan 1951-1954 (Box 3)
  - Investigation of the Department of Insurance and insurance companies 1950-1954, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Sandusky, Michigan School Audit 1953 (Box 3)
  - Investigation of Highway Department land purchases 1954 (Box 3)
- Aging (problems of) Organizations
  - Legislative Advisory Council on Problems of the Aging (Box 4)
    (John B. Martin was chair)
    - General 1957-1960, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Michigan Commission on Aging
    (John B. Martin was vice-chair, then chair)
    - General 1963-1964, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Printed material regarding problem of aging 1957-1961 (Box 4)
- Michigan Constitutional Convention 1961-1962
  - Committee on the Executive Branch
    - Minutes, memoranda, statements, action proposals, 2 volumes; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - General Convention materials: include proposals, amendments, reports of committees, printed material, etc. (Box 5)
- Michigan Crime and Delinquency Council
  - Working files 1963-1965, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Scrapbooks
  - September 1949-June 1950 (Box 6)
  - June 1950-January 1953 (Box 6)
- Sound recordings
  [Digitized audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.]
  - Campaign Spot, 1952 July, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 3 inch, 7 ½ ips
    - [Part 1], [851843-SR-1-1]; mp3 file; (1952 Senate Campaign Spot for John B. Martin's election. Note on box indicates the speaker is not Martin.)
  - Campaign Spots, 1952 July, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 15
    - [Part 1], [851843-SR-2-1]; mp3 file; (Reel 1; Three John MartinSenate campaign spots featuring Martin speaking about his political views.)
  - Campaign Spots, 1952 July, Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 15
    - [Part 1], [851843-SR-3-1]; mp3 file; (Reel 2; Three John Martin senate campaign spots featuring Martin speaking about his political views.)
  - Interview with John Martin, [Undated], Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch
    - [Part 1], [851843-SR-4-1]; mp3 file; (Interview regarding Michigan Constitutional Conventions and Martin's work on the Committee on the Executive Branch.)
- Visual Material
  - Photographs
    - Portraits (Box 6)
    - Autographed photographs of various dignitaries (Box 6)
    - JBM with such dignitaries as Nixon, Ford, MacArthur, etc. (Box 6)
    - Campaign photographs, 2 envelopes (Box 6)
    - Waterloo Recreation Area (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Motion Pictures
    - Campaign spots 1952 (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous
  - Nominating petitions for U.S. Senator 1952, 2 microfilms negative (Box 6)
  - Citations and certificates (Box 6)
Selective Index to Correspondence
Alger, Frederick Moulton, 1907-1967.
Nov. 24, 1954
Bartlett, Lynn M (Lynn Mahlon), 1904-1970.
Apr. 19, 1963
Brake, D. Hale, 1891-
July 27, 1954, July 13, 1962, Dec. 31, 1962, Jan. 30, 1963
Brown, Sanford Abbott, 1909-
Apr. 21, 1964
Cohen, Wilbur J. (Wilbur Joseph), 1913-1987.
Nov. 21, 1957
Dirksen, Everett McKinley.
Aug. 26, 1959, Sept. 1, 1959, Sept. 18, 1959
Eldersveld, Samuel James.
June 9, 1958
Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982.
Oct. 14, 1954
Ford, Gerald R., 1913-
Oct.4, 1954, Dec. 23, 1954
Miller, William Edward, 1914-
Dec. 14, 1961
Moody, Blair, 1902-1954.
Apr. 21, 1952
Pollock, James Kerr, 1898-
Mar. 20, 1963
Romney, George W., 1907-
Mar. 8, 1962, Mar. 5, 1963, June 5, 1963, Jan. 7, 1964, Jan. 17, 1964, Apr. 10, 1964, May 7, 1964, June 4, 1964, July 3, 1964, Sept.28, 1964
Sagendorph, Kent, 1902-
Oct. 8, 1954
Summerfield, Arthur Ellsworth, 1899-1972.
Dec. 9, 1954
Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953.
Oct. 27, 1951
Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.
Nov. 9, 1950
Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-
1954 ? Mar. 5, 1954, Apr. 7, 1954, July 10, 1958, Oct. 13, 1958, Apr. 21, 1959